Just probably.
Okay. Welcome
to the keynote session.
It's my great honor to welcome my
colleague, mentor, and also
office neighbor, Percy Liang.
Percy is a professor in computer
science at Stanford University.
He's also a cofounder of Together AI.
Similarly, and,
Maureen.
He is also the director of the Center for
Research on Foundation Models.
Percy has done pioneer research in
machine learning and the large English models,
ranging from squad data set to home
evaluation. To generative
agents and also to the term
of foundation model. As long as
as well as a wider range of other
contributions. His research really
shaped how we think
understanding and evaluating
large models. So
Percy knows everything about LMs. He
also teach a course at a Stanford
about a training LIMs from scratch.
He can predict the next token very
well, Even if you give them,
like, 1,000,000 token context
window. And also, he can answer
any questions that you ask him.
But with one exception, do I need
a visa to come to Brazil?
I mean, we are very, very glad that he
finally made it here, and I'm very
excited for all of us to hear his work
on open this in foundation models.
With that, please draw me to welcome Percy.
Thank you Dee for that generous introduction
thanks to all the organizers for inviting me,
and also being very
flexible and supportive of my
of rescheduling this talk.
So what happened was on Wednesday,
I went to the airport and I
went to the counter to check-in, And then the
agent says, can I see your Brazil
visa? And like,
oh, visa.
So I I pulled out
my friend Claude It's like, oh crap.
I don't have a Brazil visa. My flight is
leaving soon. And the Claude helpfully
replies, this is urgent.
US citizens do not need a
visa for Brazil. I was like,
then I said, well, what about this, way
website, brazil.vfsevisa.com?
And then it says I was wrong. I'm sorry.
So I feel pretty
foolish about the whole thing but it makes
me feel a little bit better that even Claude could
not answer this question.
So I'm really excited and, grateful
to have made it finally.
The last time I gave, I
cleared keynote was back in 2015.
So that was a different
era. That was when
NLP was, being kind of
taken over by deep learning. This was two years before the
transformers. People are mostly interested
in classification,
tagging, so machine translation.
And I was really interested in this question
of natural language understanding. How could you
get the
AI to really understand a sentence
well enough to translate into a
program that you can execute and produce the answer.
Nowadays, you call this, tool use.
And this was the challenge I presented to the ICLAR
community. Could deep learning actually
succeed in answering these type of questions?
Took many years, but by now,
the resounding answer is yes. So
last night, I
punched this, example
into into Claude.
Actually, I took the image and of course, they can parse
the image. It can generate a
program in Python, which is much more
And and it generates the correct answer.
Also gives a nice natural language
explanation. So,
despite not knowing about Visa, it can do this
task pretty well.
This is this is actually child's play. Right?
So Claude, as we know, can write
entire c compiler in Rust
So are we done?
We just just go home. I hear Rio has
some nice beaches. So
I so but I have,
forty minutes left.
So you might ask, okay, Percy,
What's the grand challenge you're bringing to
me? In 2026?
And to answer this question,
I think we have to step back and kind
of reframe things a little bit.
So iCLEAR, as you would all agree,
is a machine learning conference.
So what do machine learning
researchers do? So where the
core machine learning researcher
does is create better algorithms.
And what is the learning algorithm? It's, something
that takes training data and produces
a model. So the key question that a
machine learning researcher has to face is,
is my algorithm producing a model that
generalizes from the training data?
To the test data? So this is machine
learning one zero one. So you're, like, Percy, why
are you bothering me with this?
Because I think there's often,
kind of a confusion here, which is that
there's also another goal. Which is
if you're a model developer, your
goal is to produce better models, and a model is something
that takes the input and produces an output.
So here the key question is, how will this
model work? This is
very useful and we all benefit from
having strong models But
this is a different question than the
one about generalization.
And I think often we somehow
know, don't, make a difference between
these two, and that lens through a lot of
confusion. So how are these
two things related? Well, there's
a very simple equation that relates them.
So as a model developer,
your goal is to produce better algorithms,
to measure how good your algorithm is We're
gonna use something called, algorithmic efficiency,
could either be computer data efficiency
If you're a model developer,
then your goal is to push up the end accuracy.
And if you're a fundraiser, your goal is
to push up the amount of resources you have.
So hopefully, this makes it absolutely clear what
everyone's role in in life
is. Okay.
So now since
this is an iclear talk, we're gonna
focus on the middle part which is how do we improve
algorithmic efficiency.
And this question has actually been
pretty sharply studied by a bunch of
of papers, There's this actually a very
early open AI paper that looked at,
in the context of image classification,
that would make efficiency of neural nets increased by
a factor of 44 x over
seven years. More recent
work by epoch AI showed that
every eight months the algorithmic efficiency has
been doubling.
So there has been a lot of
progress. And in particular,
there's a lot of progress in the
frontier labs.
And there's also been a lot of progress
in the open community.
But, you know, how how can we make this
even better? So we can make
three wishes. This
is what I will wish for. So
which one is
open development? So we all write papers.
What are papers? There's this nice glossy
PDF files that we upload to archive. They
have nice introductions. Lots of
citations, some beautiful figures.
And this is great, but we
all know that underneath
the surface, is a very messy nonlinear
research process that contains tons of failed
experiments, and all of these hallway
conversations, the rationales for why things were done
in a certain way. And that
is a valuable part of the
science, but it rarely gets
shown.
And so my call
is for open development to surface all of
these things because that is
ultimately ground truth. The paper
is just a projection of that ground truth
onto something that will satisfy
Rivera too. So speaking of reviewer
two, my second wish is
for algorithms at scale.
So last year, I actually got a review
where the reviewer asked, why don't you try
this pretrained experiment on 70,000,000,000
parameter models? Thank you, Roberto,
for your insightful comments.
Well, so there's a tension here
So obviously, most of us don't
have enough resources to run things at large
scale. But this is in tension
with algorithms at small scale don't
always work at large scale.
And so what I want to hopefully
convey and convince you of
is the power of of scaling loss.
So my third wish is for predictability.
So our stated goal is improve learning
algorithms. But a stronger
goal would be to have an actual scientific
theory or understanding of what makes
a learning algorithm good. So for example,
if you understand the laws of physics, you can plan
predict planetary motion. You won't have to
run a bunch of I don't even know what experiments,
that case would be.
And and so one
way to operationalize the notion of understanding, which
is know, kind of a vague, is
if you can predict the outcome of an experiment
before you run it.
And in many areas of science, this is called preregistration.
You call your shots before you actually do the
experiment. And I'm going to also talk
about how we should do more of this.
So I'm gonna talk about all three wishes
in the context of Marin.
So what is Moran?
Marin's goal is train the best language model
we can given the available
resources and do it openly. So it
started in 2024 at Stanford
as a as a as a research
project. And since
last year, it's been developed full time.
By OpenAthena, so include Stanford,
OpenAthena folks, and some
folks in the broader community. And
a big thanks to Google for providing some
compute to support this project. And
so, Marin, I'll show you, fulfills these
three wishes.
But it wasn't always like this in
Moran. So when we
started, it was the dark ages.
So in November 28,
2024, 12PM,
we decided to conduct our, first
expedition wanted to train a 8,000,000,000
parameter model. Because that seems like what you
do. We didn't really know what we were
doing, but we would just say, okay. Let's let's
just try to make it
work. With under one condition.
Which is that we never turn back.
So this is the journey.
So we started took
the best data set that we thought was out there, which
was this, DCLM dataset.
We had some TPUs.
We trained for a bit.
We switched hardware. We kept
on training. At some point, we started
turning down the learning rate. Because that helps
the model converge better.
Produces ultimately the final checkpoint.
And then, we said,
okay. Actually, we have some time. Why don't in,
Nematron CC was another dataset released
by NVIDIA. So we decided, okay.
Let's train on that data. For a
quite some time. And then we did another
cool down. So
along the way, were
many many adventures. I will just mention one of them.
So one thing that happened when we started
cooling down the learning rate is
that the training loss was actually started
going down and then it started increasing.
As the
as the learning rate was decreasing. So
we were very, very puzzled by this.
So if you're watching this video online,
you can pause the video and try to think
what, might be going on.
So So the first thing you do, of
course, you go and look how you want these
lechaptics norms. And we
saw this norm, which is the LM
head norm was was blowing up.
So this is no good.
We've fixed it. We added,
z loss, which is the this
regularizer that keeps the norms under control.
And then the run.
You know, finished. So this is one example
of something we had to firefight, midstream.
So we added a different loss function towards
the end. Couldn't have
started over. And somehow
we ended up with a model, 3.1
base. On 14 out of 19
datasets. So I thought this was not a
bad start.
For not knowing what we're doing.
So last year,
we did took our second expedition,
We decided to be a bit more ambitious.
We decided to train out of marine 32.
Billion parameter model.
So, this one
was a little bit different.
So here's the training loss. It's
going down. But you see that the
loss is spiking.
Quite often. And
so we were a little bit disturbed by
this. But, you
know, when the loss spikes, it seems to go
back down. And continue. It's like
you you get sick and then you recover. So
maybe this is just part of So we
asked our friends who knew stuff.
What's happening, and half of them said, you'll
be fine and half of them said you won't be fine.
And it turned out that the half that said, we
won't be fine were right because one day we got hit by
the bad spike. And by the bad spike, spikes
up and then it doesn't return.
To its original resting spot.
So this this run was cooked.
Alright. So so now,
imagine using the ship analogy, Now
there's a hole in your hole and now what do you do?
Okay. So we we we panic.
We, let's try clipping the updates
to make sure that the we roll back, of course.
Then we clip the updates, didn't
work. We said, okay. These updates look
too large. Let's skip them. Didn't work. We
tried a different optimizer, Muon, which is in fashion.
That sort of worked until it didn't work.
So this was this was bad. And
then finally, we said, okay,
we'll add this another
normal norm term called QK norm.
Which basically takes your query and key
measures and scales by the Frovenius,
norm. Of that.
So it's it's,
you know, we knew about this.
I suppose we were a little bit too proud to add
it because we didn't need it for
our AP run, and it was fine. We actually
tried a 70 b run for a little bit without it, and
it was kind of fine too. So
we thought, we don't need this. And in
general, norms are not free. Right? They provide
stability, but they reduce your dynamic range. So you
don't want to
add too many. But this
time, know, we had no choice. We
added norm. And then it was
smooth sailing from then on.
Until we started doing cool
down then the loss training loss jumps
up and this time stays high.
So so what's going on here? So this is
a different pattern. So you're watching
on that video, pause the video,
and, try to think what you would do here.
So normally when you see
stuff like this, this is not a loss spike.
Usually means that there's some distribution shift
in your your data. Now it's like
this distribution of data is, like, harder.
But we're training on the same data. We're not changing
the data. So then we finally tracked
this down to the random
shuffle of our data was not
random enough. And
because we were trying to save costs
and there was easier to use,
a a poorer shuffle. So once we fix
that, that that was fine.
Okay. And I also improved the valve losses,
and we ended up
finally with Marin 32 base.
It was the best open source base
model. For twenty days.
And then, I think Omo three
came out and Nematron came
out with models. These these, know,
lifespan of these models is,
weeks, I would say, if if you have that.
But we were very happy to be the best open
source based model for for a
non zero amount of time.
So Okay. So reflections.
So during these YOLO expeditions,
I thought it was a good learning experience.
So we saw that many things can go wrong.
From just
dumb implementation bugs to actually more subtle
ML bugs. To
things that might not even be considered
bugs, and how to debug
and rescue a life run
is an important life scale. That hopefully
all of you will develop.
The general you know, sometimes in life,
you just can't roll back and fix it.
And restart. So you have to kind of go on.
Now then we've got some
respectable models. You know, they were kind of,
you know, better than some of our,
competitors. Especially given the resources
that we had. It's certainly not the best
we could have done with the resources that we had.
And I'm pretty sure if we try to scale to
1,000,000,000,000 parameters with more resources, we
probably would have shipped that too. And
finally, scientifically, as a scientist,
I find this very displeasing.
So now we talk
about enlightenment.
So suppose someone walks up to you
and say, I'm gonna give you
one e 25 flops.
So this is something like 1,000
b two hundreds for, like, a
a month or two or something. So
what model would you train? Okay.
You know, so clearly, this
is know, kind of hard question
to answer. And the problem is
that there's just a lot of design decisions.
That go into training your model. You have
to specify the shape of the model architecture,
and then there's batch size, learning rate, the
schedule, all these things.
And how how do you set them?
You and and it's important to set them
right. Here's a study that my
students, did. Where
just by tuning the learning rate,
you can get a factor
of two's, you know, speed up.
So that's just one
you know, parameter.
So the the problem is that
you don't have
enough compute to go and say train
your 1,000,000,000,000 parameter model
and do hyperparameter sweeps at that scale.
It's just too expensive. Even the frontier
labs don't want it. I mean, it it would be ridiculous to
do this, no matter how much computer you have.
So therefore, you must choose
the config at small scale. So do
the hyperparameter sweeps, ablations at small
scale. And
the thing that you must
have is that somehow the small
scale losses have to be predictive
of losses at full scale.
So that's the kind of the this
the scaling mindset.
But wait, you say. There's a thing called
emergence. Right? As models get
larger, somehow they
they you go from zero to all of
a sudden they're doing things. So if you're only
doing experiments
at small scale, you just wouldn't see
these phenomena. And that's
there's some no truth to that, but there's
been also papers that show well,
first predict a smooth metric and then you could regress
the accuracy, this is actually
just you know, okay. I wouldn't
say this is, like, a solved problem, but this
is manageable.
But then you say, optimizers
are also scaled to peta. So from the
same optimizer paper,
we looked across, a few different optimizers.
Across model scale. We see
that if you were at a 130,000,000
parameters, you would see enjoy
40% speed ups.
Of things like muon and soap over your
your model. But when you go to
only 1,200,000,000 parameter models,
the speed up goes down to 10%.
And you can imagine if it scales up,
you know, I don't know what will happen. It'll probably,
you know, shrink even. Potentially
more.
And also, you know, data filtering
is scale dependent. So we did
this, experiment. Done
by Michael Ryan, who took,
a bunch of common crawl tokens,
so 3,000 works
of common crawl. And try different
data filtering and transformations on them to
and then train a one b model.
What's the best data filtering strategy?
This is a problem that's been studying a literature
but it turns out to be very scale dependent.
And the the problem is that if you
have let's say a very aggressive
data filtering and you produce something like
find y b d u, things look
fine. And then they start
you you start kind of as you've trained more tokens, you
start there. DCLM
and and, Nemotron are are better
but even though they start kind of overfitting
eventually. So if you were
over here, if you had a less
scale, then you would prefer
let's say, DCLM, But if
you're a larger scale, DCLM
might be too aggressive.
So this scale dependence makes
things difficult. This is something
to keep in mind as you're reading a paper that
makes a certain claim You always have to
think about what scale is this operating at because
the conclusions might be
But the the key thing is that we
we don't give up.
Right? Because scale dependence
and predictability can
coexist.
You just because things
that on scale, doesn't mean
that you have to know, throw
everything up. And
the way to address this
is by thinking about a scaling
recipe. So we're used to doing
a training run We've put a
config file with some hyperparameters.
But I want you to not think about that.
I want you to think about, a function
that maps amount of compute
you have to a setting of the hyperparameter.
So no matter what compute I give you, you should be
able to tell me what hyperparameters That's
a scaling recipe. So
it's it's one level above just a config
file. And you
can also have, two dimensional
scaling recipe where you have, number of
parameters in your model and the dataset. And
you predict the hyperparameter.
K. So here's an example. I'll just get in the recipe.
I'll talk more about this in a bit.
Where given the hidden dimension, which ultimately controls
the number of parameters, you set the
hidden dimension the number of layers
to h divided by something
plus log h, number of tension heads,
the initialization,
you know, the various, constants
on Adam and and so on.
And so this is an example of a scaling
recipe. I don't know if this is a good scaling
recipe or not, but it's a skimming recipe.
So once you have a scaling recipe,
then you can go and fit scaling well.
I think this is something that's maybe underappreciated
is that everyone sees skating laws and they're like, oh, great.
All you're doing is trying to figure out,
given a compute budget, how do I split it between
number of parameters and and dataset
size? But I think the key thing
to even start to is getting
a slide is that given
a number of parameters, dataset
size, actually does not specify
the configuration. You have to manual
you have to fill in the details, and the details matter
here as we'll see. So let's suppose
you have a scaling recipe though. So
this has, been
quite well studied. The classic, chinchilla
scaling laws algorithm two, which is isoflav
curves. Basically,
what it says is that let's try a
bunch of different compute budgets.
Maybe from six e,
18 all the way to three e
21. And for each
compute budget, what I'm going to do
is I'm gonna sweep try different number of
parameters is
n. And then that determines
based on the compute budget and
the number of parameters, the dataset size just by
dividing. And I can train a model and
I get a loss. Okay. So
then at this point, for every compute budget,
I can just find the minimum of
this quadratic looking like
thing. And say that is the
compute optimal point. Given that amount
of compute, I get the most,
the the lowest loss by setting the number of parameters
in this way. And
then second, you you basically,
you know, you you can plot that,
you can draw a line basically that
connects all the minimum and that gives you your
extrapolation to new
new, losses. Sorry. New
compute budgets.
Okay. So that's a review of what Chinchilla's scaling
laws means. Okay. So
using this framework, which has been around for a
while, remember
the hard part is figuring out the scaling
recipe. So here is our first
attempt at a scaling recipe. So
we set the weight decay to 0.1.
And then there's a bunch of all these
things and there were
there have been a bunch of papers that studied
each of these things
in isolation. For example, the this
this paper shows that the the learning rates
of scale as the square root of
the batch size This says that you
should the beta two term in Adam should
be changing as
a a function of the batch size as well.
There's a scaling for the depth.
Then this is the so called muting initialization,
which says, as you scale your
model, how do you initialize your prompt?
Okay. So using
the scaling recipe, we did the
textbook isoflop curves. So we fit
a bunch of isoflops we found the minimums,
and then we fit a line, and
then the line looks pretty good pretty
good. And then, uh-oh. So
then it starts getting 2.5%
error. And then at
this point, the run just diverges.
So we're just not
good.
So one important
point I want to make is that scaling laws
don't happen automatically.
You have to will them into existence
If you have a bad scaling recipe,
you don't get a skating lie. Or at least a clean
one.
Okay. So so how do I debug this
now? So
suspected that the learning rate was too high.
Weight decay, we just set it to 0.1, which
is probably suboptimal with should
change.
And now know, how do you solve this? So
remember in the dark ages, we
just you know, we just hacked it.
We okay. The learning rate seem to be blowing up. Let's lower
the learning rate. But and
you can do that. And we can get this
run to not diverge. But that's
not the problem. Problem is that, okay,
this run is fine. Then what about the next
scale and the next scale and the next scale after that? We don't have a if
we don't have a story or we don't have a
scaling recipe, then we're gonna be
debugging every single run. It's gonna be a a YOLO
run. So what we need
to do instead is to step back and
fix the scaling recipe instead.
So So we did
two main fixes and a bunch of small
fixes. So the first thing
is that this is a sounder weight
update. So you take your optimizer,
which could be Adam, could be a muon,
You get an update And
then you take your weights, and you
take a step in that direction, And
Lambda's, the weight decays, so you also shrink your
your weights towards zero. So this
is the standard thing. And
the the problem is this. That
this lambda is kind of controlling
both how fast you move and also the norm, and it's
we don't really have great control over the wire norm.
If I tell you that lambda is 0.1,
I don't know what the norm of those weights
are. And remember, from
our experience that controlling
norm of these, these models
really matters. So
then, we did this sort of
in hindsight, the kind of obvious thing. Which is that
let's just normalize all the things.
Which means that take your update, we're gonna
normalize it, and then,
then we're gonna take an update on that normalized,
update. We're gonna normalize again just for good
luck. So geometrically,
what this looks like is that we're here
and the update sends
us in that direction. And we're gonna normalize
it and
end up on the hyper So this is why it's
kind of optimization All the
norms are by construction
normalized. So this gives
us very explicit control via this,
constant r.
So this turned out to be a pretty
good idea. So remember at,
some of the larger scales,
we were getting diminishing returns and
10%
speed up. Now this is getting
giving us a more like a 20 to 30%,
you know, speed up. Even over muon.
Which is great. But the
other thing that I think is even
you know, more interesting is that
using this hyperball optimizer,
allows the hyperparameters to be
transferred across model scales.
So if you use, Adam w,
then you see that for every scale,
the optimal hyperparameter is kind of shifting
around. Whereas if you use a hyperball
optimizer, it's relatively stable.
And stable hyperparameters are good
because that way your scaling recipe can be
a very simple form. And
this also happens, with muon.
Okay. So the second fix is this observation
that the learning rate should probably
decrease with more tokens. So there's this paper
by Bjork et al that shows that
as you increase the number of tokens that you're
training on, the optimal
learning rate is shifting over to the left.
Okay? So again, remember
just because the optimum
scale dependent doesn't mean that
it's game over. As long as you can kind of predictably
ride this this, this wave, then you'll
be fine. So
hence, so now we came up
with our updated scaling recipe.
So using that last insight, we
had, used a number of,
tokens, which is number that you train on,
and scale raise it to the 0.3 power.
So there's nothing magical about 0.3.
It probably could have been us know, slightly different
as well. And
then now because we're using Adam h, we don't
have this, scaling by
h term. You can see a bunch of other
smaller changes
as as well, but most everything else is kind of the
same. And then we'd also did
kind of a more rigorous hyperparameter
sweep of the of the kind of the smaller
model And
then we said, okay.
If we really believe this our,
our theory,
you can call it theory. Then
we're gonna preregister this.
So all of Moran development is happening
on GitHub. So
Will Held, who did all this self scaling work,
basically commented saying, we did a
public preregistration of expected
results. At these
flop counts would expect this kind
of loss. And then,
so then we
we started training. So
this picture shows you the
ISO flop curves that we got from our smaller models.
We've remember we fit a scaling law
and that tells us loss
predictions on
know, in principle, larger and larger models.
And we this we fitted
on these isofo curves and made
predictions out here. These
predictions were pretty good. They're pretty on
on target. And then we started training this.
And we waited for a while,
And then, just a few weeks
ago, this finished.
And we basically nailed this. So this is within
0.005. Of
of the flops. Didn't
diverge, didn't wasn't two point, 2%
error. So
this this is good news. Really good news.
Right? Because were
able to predict how well we're gonna do
on this run which is 300
times larger than the models that
we were training before.
So this means that you can experiment
at 300 times less smaller
scale and still
have a chance of predicting what's gonna
happen at the larger scale.
And that was just, perplexity
on some, you know, text from
Paloma. We
also show that,
via, observational skin loss, you can take
these complexity and turn them into actual
downstream evaluations. We can predict those
well. As well.
So
reflections here.
So I encourage you to
think about scaling recipes. Not individual
runs.
It takes work and also
restraint to get a clean skating law.
And this is really not, I think, how the
standard way people do
things. Right? Because if it
the learning rate is too big, you lower it.
But the problem with doing that is that now
you're back into this individual run mindset,
and it doesn't tell you at all how you
should deal with I give you
10 times more compute.
Now fortunately for us,
was already a lot of great work studying the effects
of the depth and the batch size and number of tokens.
So we were kind of assembling these results and trying
to adapt it to our current setting.
This worked pretty well. We were able to predict
out extrapolate out 300 x
But, you know, I don't wanna be overconfident
here. I am not sure how
far this can go. 300,
I think, is already pretty ambitious,
and I think one problem
with, larger scales is that the numeric
stability of training could start
eating into you, whereas it's a less of a factor at smaller
scale. So this is new
territory for us, so we don't know
quite yet. But let's
just say let's go up to one e 23
flops. The next
step then, given this that we have
one scheme of SOP, is to iterate
on the algorithm which includes both the architecture
and the training algorithm, as well as
the scaling recipe, and see if we
can make the losses better.
Remember, the whole point of scaling loss
is now now the fun begins. Now
we can run small experiments
and have something to drive
down. Where we have some confidence that this
is actually gonna translate to larger
scale in a predictable way.
So Okay. So then main obvious
thing was you know, everyone's doing a mixture
of experts because these are more compute,
you know, efficient.
And it introduced
new challenges because you have all
these experts that
can become you know, unbalanced.
And so there's low balancing techniques that are
needed not to mention a bunch of other
things. So we didn't do a mixture of experts initially
because we were saying if we can't even get
the dense training to work, then we have no hope
at the MOE. So now the dense training
worked pretty well. So now let's
try MOE. So
this one actually much smoother than
I expected. It seems like a lot of the hard work
from the dense actually just,
dense models translated
over with a few I guess, hiccups.
By the way, all these experiments, I'm gonna
try to put these GitHub issues. You
can go read them. They'll have
all the gory details about, what we tried.
So these are pretty nice Isoflop.
You know, curves.
And using these, we could, we can
extrapolate, and we saw that from the dense
model, even our initial
MOE got a 3.76,
speed up. And then we,
over the course of two,
and and that led to another 1.5
speed up. So this is things were going,
you know, pretty well here.
And then, so
Larry Dial is a person who's been iterating on
on these architectures. There
are a ton of different
issues. Corresponding to different
things that we want to try. So
the game is once we have reliable scaling
laws, then we go and try
know, different tension gates, change the number of
experts, and know, let's
see if we remove gait and norm.
And try all sorts of ablations and
additions. For each of
these, I think the scaling recipe is a
good starting point And
depending on the intervention may or may not require
tweaking the scaling recipe.
So these are ongoing. And,
you see that these are all labeled agent,
MOE experiment. Because right
now, m o, Marin is basically using
know, agents to go do the experiments for us.
Which works some other time, I would
say. Okay. So back
to preregistration. So our
MOE recipe seems to be, solid.
So then it already kicked off a 120,000,000,000
parameter model run.
16,000,000,000 active parameters. So this
this is a one e 23 flops MOU
run. So this is now getting you know, pretty
respectable. It's not it's not,
you know, deep seek, but it's it's,
think it's, it's not bad.
And but the important thing is that
now we've, again, preregistered that
one e 23 should get a loss of
2.52. So this run is not
done yet. But check back in a in
a week or or so and
we'll hopefully have the prediction.
Okay. So just as a kind of a interlude
here, I've talked about language
models so far. But the exact
same machinery can be actually and the infrastructure
can be a applied to other
types of modalities. So two things
I'll just quickly point out. So
there's this work
on using all of the Moran
infrastructure, the code, and the scaling
recipes. For audio
modeling. And
it basically worked.
And, another Eric, Zach is
working on
using scanning loss to
train models on on DNA.
So if you're interested, follow that GitHub
issue. And, and, basically,
the you know, things are working.
So I think this is great news because
you know, remember, the job of a machine
researcher is to create
learning algorithms. That generalize
and this is sort of ultimate test. It a
DNA and audio are very different you know, modalities.
And if we have something
that actually works for these modalities, then
means we're doing something right.
So Okay. So
finally, I wanna talk a bit about data.
So So
the OpenCV community is actually doing
a fantastic job of producing many great
data sets, both for pretraining, for mid
training, for and
so on. And,
so what is our strategy in on Marin?
So currently, it's
basically take all the tokens we can find.
It could be for pretraining, could be mid training,
post training. Could be synthetic or real,
We should make sure that these pass some sort
of reasonable quality bar, but the
bar isn't that even that high.
And importantly, we should make sure that tokens
are actually appropriate license.
So that we don't get in legal trouble.
So this is the current stat. This you can
go to this URL, and you can see an
up to date data, status of
what the Marin, dataset looks like.
So so far, we've accumulated 18,000,000,000,000
tokens datasets.
Much of this is web, some of this
is a lot of this is Nemotron datasets.
Some Hugging Face to find, PDFs,
and so on and so forth.
So So using
once we have all this data,
now there's a separate set of questions which is,
how do you train this dataset?
And the two important things to consider
is, mixtures and curricula.
The general framework that we've been adopting
is that gonna be a bunch of stages
in training. You can call them
pretraining, mid training, post training if you like, but I'm
just gonna call them stage one and stage two and
stage three two. Because the
semantics, I don't think matter.
And are blurry anyway. For
each stage, for each of the data
sources, I'm gonna have a distribution over
that, over that data set.
So now what we're gonna do
is, go back to our bag
of tricks and say, well, we're gonna
train
and then I'm going to fit a parametric
model that can predict the loss
on some configuration. And now
I'm going to optimize this, parametric
you know, function. And find the config that
gives me the lowest loss. And then we're
just gonna use that config at scale
fold this into the scaling laws, but now we can
be sort of,
naive about this. So this is
still active work. I don't have,
results to share today, but you can go to this
issue and follow what we're doing.
Actually, I do have well, I do have one
slide, of results.
This plot shows essentially
each point here is a particular
data mixture or slash curriculum.
And this has been sorted by,
complexity,
Lower is better. And we can see that
many of these mixtures are pretty bad,
the the mixture that we came up with
is actually, you know, really
good, and it outperforms some of
these, standard you know, baselines.
But, you know, this is still very preliminary,
so I I think we need to robust
Sapphire before we can be confident
in this.
So reflections on data.
So despite the common wisdom
that data is everything,
you know, I've actually spent very little time
on it. And that's not because
it's not important. That's just because the community
has done such a great job of curating datasets
that we're sort of just building on top of what the community
has. For now.
It's interesting to note also that data
is something that is easy for the
community to paralyze.
And in particular, also if you create a dataset,
it can be used multiple times. Whereas
if you train a model, the compute is used
up and is is gone. So in some sense,
data is this kind of evergreen more
renewable, resource.
So that's why I I tend to
say that I get really excited about dataset
releases because then these can power
additional models as opposed to
just you know, model releases.
So a few
other notes. So we
have 18,000,000,000,000 tokens.
Deepgram v four was trained on 32,000,000,000,000. Frontier
Lab, models are trained on
presumably even more.
And so we still don't
have enough tokens, let alone kind of high quality
tokens. I mean, in some sense, we have enough tokens because if
you take common crawl, it's a 100,000,000,000,000
tokens. But much of that is, stuff that
you don't probably wanna train on directly.
And in particular, we're missing high quality
coding and agenda So there's still a lot of
data work, to be done. Before we
can have really, strong models.
Okay. So last part, I'm gonna talk and
reflect about openness.
So So if you look at these
logos,
you'll realize that many of them are familiar.
And it's really hard, I think, to go
in life without touching at least one of
these, either directly or indirectly.
And if you haven't guessed it,
all these are open source software projects. So it's
very clear that open source software has been a
spectacular success. It wasn't always
this way. So the story
of open source software is actually kind of interesting,
and you can read more about this. So
in the sixties and seventies when software was
first a even a a
thing really. It was open.
You know, people it came with hardware.
Which was a thing that people was
commercializing. And it was just shared.
If your software didn't work, you just go in
and you fix it. You share it with your friends.
It was only until the nineteen eighties
where people realized that you can make money off
of this stuff. And when that
happens, things close off. So in particular,
Microsoft was born in
the eighties and, Unix as as well,
which was actually open, became closed.
And then in reaction to that, there was a open
source movement, which started with, Richard
Stallman, Agnew, and Linus, and Linux.
And open source, the term didn't get coined
until 1998. But
then in the February, this is when it really took
off. With, prominent backers like
IBM and Google in the early days.
Open source has been it's hard
to imagine the the the
you know, the digital ecosystem without open
source software.
So I will say that AI in 2026
is where software was in 1999.
So for those of you who are old enough, remember
the Linux versus Windows,
you know, fights. And
And the the history of you
know, AI is that for much
of the history up until the twenty tens,
things were very open, people published,
there were open data sets and frameworks.
And, of course, now much of the
the frontier, if not all of the frontier is is
closed.
So but what does open in AI mean?
And this term has been
kind of abused, quite a bit. So
you know, there's you know, Mark saying
that open a source AI is a path forward.
And, open
source initiative claiming that you
know, rightly, that Meta's LLAMA is
still not, you know, open source.
Is a taxonomy. Just to
get the term straight. So we know what closed
models are. You can only access them via API.
We know what open weight models are.
These are models that where
you see the weights, but you don't have the code. You don't have the
data. It's like a binary executable
that you can run
and this is sometimes people call this open source.
But true open source is
where you have the code and the data recipe,
which includes works like
OMON, Nematron. So Marin takes
this one step further and
is what I call open development.
So it's everything
and in in addition, you can see the process
and can contribute. And
this open development is actually really
important because in software,
actually, open source software is already
open development. Here is a Linux
GitHub repo. It's just sitting there.
Right? You can go there today and
submit a poll request.
Linus will probably reject it, but nonetheless,
you can you can do it.
And this is the way it works.
Know, all Linus
used to say, enough eyes, all bugs are
shallow. Everything is out there. They're
discussion. That's the true spirit of open source.
And in Marin,
we've been fortunate to have a number of contributions
you know, from the community as we build,
we share our work, People are,
are noticing and and contributing.
And, you know, we also have a a Discord
where we discuss all the
all the things that we're doing. So
free to join.
And maybe, a kind of optimistic
retrospective is that in
a few years, maybe that AI
will follow the same trend as open source,
where it started open, went closed,
and then in the
in some time, this decade,
maybe truly open models will be good
enough to be on the worthy
infrastructure.
So going back to the original question, what is the
grand challenge for iCleo
twenty twenty six?
I would say that there's still a
ton of work to be done on just
core there's many other things to do as well,
but even just a core bread and butter
of machine learning
if you think about it from the perspective of
you know, having the most data or compute
efficient algorithm, we just don't know. We don't
even know where the ceiling is. And there's my
I I guarantee you there's a
lot of work to be done here.
And I highlight this because
you know, many people are chasing accuracy.
But that requires you to
have resources.
And, you know, many of us,
But in order to do that,
I think we have to kind of shift
our mindset in terms of how
we operate. And I think
the three wishes that I have
are in line with hopefully making
it possible for us to
you know, truly innovate on the algorithm
mix aside. So open development,
I think today research, as you can all agree,
is changing. We have you know,
this deluge of papers, we have agents,
So know, I think open development, as I see it, is
kind of just you
know, they're embracing the chaos and say, we're just going
to just go to the full ex
extreme and make everything open.
And the secret plan
is that now agents can use that context
to further, improve
research. Probably faster than any
of us, can.
Scaling laws.
A lot of people think of scaling laws as
you know, large and larger models.
But I actually want you to think about scaling laws as smaller
and smaller models.
Right? I think it's embracing it's
skin loss means that you can do ablations on smaller scale,
not more scale. And I hope that
reviewer too will eventually say,
instead of where's that 70,000,000,000 primary
model, we'll say, you know, where is this
gain log? Because I personally would prefer
to have much more predictable
you know, sense of how the
the models are gonna work at a large scale
than a single point.
And finally, predictability.
Predictability is really about
do you know what you're doing?
And which means that you have
kind of a handle on your
method. That is strong enough
that you can make predictions about what
your risk experiments are gonna be before you run
them. Now there's always gonna be things that
happen. There's always gonna be error.
But and in order to prove it,
I would, you know, encourage and maybe challenge all
of you to try preregistering
your results.
Okay. So Marin was made possible
by a ton of people
David Hall, Will
Hall, Russell, Larry Raval. I'm
not gonna read all these names, but
Raul, and Raul and Ramon, special tank
because they are the infra team, and we all know that infra
is very valuable and
that enables research to happen David
was the first you know, person
who and I started talking about
wanting to do something as
back as, early as 2022,
and Will and Larry have been, build
all those are kind of full time OpenAthena.
Folks, and there's a lot of students, some of which are in this
room who have contributed to this.
Effort. And thanks to Alec also for giving
us some valuable inspiration and
hints. Okay. So with that,
I will conclude. Happy to take any questions.
Okay.
If you have any questions, please use
the Mac here.
Hi, Percy. Very nice talk. Thank you. I'm wondering,
what you think the relationship is or how you view the
relationship between Marin and
AI two's open releases. And I think
there's some open models from MPZU
AI as well that I think have a
similar philosophy of also releasing the code
and the process and spawn.
Yeah. What is the
difference between Marin and AI two and the the the
l m is it LM three
sixty? Yeah. Yeah. Project?
I think all of these are in somehow the
same neighborhood of wanting to promote
openness. These, I think, would all
be considered, you know, open
source. Marin tries to go one
step further and in terms of open
development. Because
today, you can go to a Moran and you can see what we're
doing. You know, people ask me
what's on the Marin roadmap.
It's like, okay, it's it's out there in public. I can send
you the GitHub. URL.
I think this is
something that is more open than
even kind of an academia where, typical
they accustomed to. I think many
most, I think, projects are more
the do a bunch of closed work and then
drop everything openly. Which is
good. I mean, more, you know, more openness
is always better than less openness.
But I think it's the open development that
allows us to do these things like preregistration
and getting community contributions and so on.
So scaling laws seem,
you know, very nice to have.
You had to do a lot of work it seems like to get
those scaling laws to apply.
How do you know when you're doing experiments
on the small models now that you're not gonna
just undo some of that work and
revert back to a model that doesn't actually
scale in practice. So like, you have a stable
model that does scale, but you want to experiment
on it, it seems like you might have to redo the
scaling experiments every time you make some
change. Yeah. Yeah. So
would say scaling laws are challenging.
And I don't think we've you know, solved
everything far from it.
What I will say that and sometimes building
a scaling law that is reliable
requires additional compute.
But I the way I see Marin is that
know, this is a platform that
everyone in this room or not in this room can
can use. We've done the work to validate
some of this gain laws. Which means that
hopefully that gives you the ability to use those
scaling laws to do smaller
scale experiments. With
some hope that these will scale.
And then I think if the the results
are promising, we'll actually go
and you know, you can submit a
PR. We'll work with you to
to try to scale that.
You can think about this clinical trials.
At the end of the day, you can only do so much in
of in in the lab.
You have to test it out on at scale to know
whether you're right.
Hi. So from your scaling recipe,
slide, it's a seems like you looked at
a lot of research that looks individually at
like batch size, depth, and
so on. So can you sort of
assume that these are orthogonal
factors, or do you need to consider the interaction between
them? As well when you make a scaling
recipe? Yeah. So all those factors
definitely some of they definitely interact.
And you know, there's
only so much grid search you can really
do. What we do is, at the smallest
scale, we do do a fairly comprehensive,
you know, sweep and
then when the the recipe
when we give the parametric forms, we
are using heuristics which
are you know, based on papers or
I ideas of how things ought
to to work. And
and to scale up.
Now some of those might learn
that might be mistaken, and then we have
to go back to a drawing board and see what
what works. But so far,
it seems like things are
independent enough that, it's well
behaved. Thank you.
Hi. Thanks for the inspiring talk.
I'd like to know if you have any, experiments
or, insights on
how many isoflops curves
we have to have and how many points
on those curves that will
be reliable enough for us
to derive the Scania loss?
Yeah. So how many are so far
points do you need in curves? I mean, we basically
use seven, and I don't
the number of points per isoflot
is I mean, I guess maybe
one thing is question of
if you have good guesses of where the optimum is
gonna be, then you can sample
around there.
I think some of these are probably over
done. The
other factor is that sometimes we do
care about this regime
on the right. Because this corresponds to
overtraining. Which even though it's
not compute optimal, there might be inference reasons
to sample that space.
So we are probably doing more than we absolutely
need to just to get a better understanding
of the space. Thank you.
Hi. Thanks so much for the talk.
Yesterday, Alec gave a really nice talk
on DCGAN. Where he reran some of his
old experiments from ten years ago and
found that, like, if you were to do like a distribution
over 300 of these DC
GAN ablations or hyperparameter search,
maybe like only half of his
ideas that he'd post ten years ago still held up.
So I was wondering, do you think ten years
from now if we're looking back at these scaling recipes, that there
will be some of these ideas that held up better than
others? Or are there ones that you think are more
likely to hold? Yeah.
That's a good question. I certainly
don't think many of these
I think some of these things will
continue to hold.
I mean, ten years is a long time.
If you look at some of these, you
know, principles, these are not even
specific to language models. They've been you know,
been, vetted in the in
the vision you know, community, like, you know,
ten years ago.
I think that clearly a lot
will change.
I would say that probably a lot
of the the mindset and the intuitions
around these things will hopefully still
continue to hold even if the architectures, which
I hope will will evolve into
something better.
So my question is the following.
Imagine the everything goes great
and there are thousands and thousands of people proposing
suggestions for experiments
and new architectures and new scales.
How do we prioritize which
runs to do?
And, also in
a world where there's willing to contribute
to compute,
how, can we score, like,
how much
each run is contributing to the overall
goal? Yeah. I think
that would be a great problem to have if,
there's thousands of people
wanting to contribute ideas. The way I think
about it is that there should be
a minimum scale
where any researcher should be able to you
know first of all, vet some sort of idea locally.
And then
on Marin, we'll give you a kind
of a maybe one
I don't know, I don't wanna promise anything, but,
like, one eighteen or
even 19 flops depending on number of submissions.
Then again, it's kind of like
clinical trials where the things that are
obviously bad we just don't.
You know. That that's feedback.
Go back to the drawing board. Things
that are promising we kind of run at the next,
scale and so on and so forth. Now
the challenge actually with a thousand different
things is that you how
do you combine them? And when
you combine them, do they stack?
Or do they interfere with each other? And
that's another dimension which we haven't
had to really address
yet because you know, most of our development is fairly
serial. But if you have
you know, I I think large organizations that are developing
models have this problem all the time.
In which case you need to
you know, exercise judgment. But I think that's
also a sort of meta research problem
how to combine different,
you know, ideas and
make them compatible. Example,
you can sample a bunch of random things
and run tournaments. But
that's a great thing to consider. Thank
you. Okay. Let's thank Percy
again.
Okay. So thank you everyone
for participating
So this formally conclude
our event conference. We looking forward
to see you all here tomorrow for
the workshops.